<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/​ns/​1.0'>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mrs. Dalloway in Bond Street</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Dial Publishing Company</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Chapter 1</head>
                <p>Mrs Dallowaysaid she would buy the gloves herself.
                Big Benwas striking as she stepped out into the street. It was eleven
                o'clock and the unused hour was fresh as if issued to children on a
                beach. But there was something solemn in the deliberate swing of the
                repeated strokes; something stirring in the murmur of wheels and the
                shuffle of footsteps.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>No doubt they were not all bound on errands of happiness. There is much
                more to be said about us than that we walk the streets of Westminster.
                Big Ben too is nothing but steel rods consumed by rust were it not for
                the care of H. M.'s Office of Works. Only for Mrs Dalloway the moment
                was complete; for Mrs Dalloway June was fresh. A happy childhood--and it
                was not to his daughters only that Justin Parry had seemed a fine fellow
                (weak of course on the Bench); flowers at evening, smoke rising; the caw
                of rooks falling from ever so high, down down through the October
                air--there is nothing to take the place of childhood. A leaf of mint
                brings it back; or a cup with a blue ring.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>Poor little wretches, she sighed, and pressed forward. Oh, right under
                the horses' noses, you little demon! and there she was left on the kerb
                stretching her hand out, while Jimmy Dawes grinned on the further side.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>A charming woman, poised, eager, strangely white-haired for her pink
                cheeks, so Scope Purvis, C. B., saw her as he hurried to his office. She
                stiffened a little, waiting for Durtnall's van to pass. Big Ben struck
                the tenth; struck the eleventh stroke. The leaden circles dissolved in
                the air. Pride held her erect, inheriting, handing on, acquainted with
                discipline and with suffering. How people suffered, how they suffered,
                she thought, thinking of Mrs Foxcroft at the Embassy last night decked
                with jewels, eating her heart out, because that nice boy was dead, and
                now the old Manor House (Durtnall's van passed) must go to a cousin.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>"Good morning to you!" said Hugh Whitbread raising his hat rather
                extravagantly by the china shop, for they had known each other as
                children. "Where are you off to?"</p>
                <p>"I love walking in London" said Mrs Dalloway. 
                "Really it's better than walking in the country!"</p>
                <p>"We've just come up" said Hugh Whitbread. "Unfortunately to see
                doctors."</p>
                <p>"Milly?" said Mrs Dalloway, instantly compassionate.</p>
                <p><"Out of sorts," said Hugh Whitbread. "That sort of thing. Dick
                all right?"</p>
                <p>"First rate!" said Clarissa.</p>

                <p>Of course, she thought, walking on, Milly is about my
                age--fifty--fifty-two. So it is probably that, Hugh's manner had said
                so, said it perfectly--dear old Hugh, thought Mrs Dalloway, remembering
                with amusement, with gratitude, with emotion, how shy, like a
                brother--one would rather die than speak to one's brother--Hugh had
                always been, when he was at Oxford, and came over, and perhaps one of
                them (drat the thing!) couldn't ride. How then could women sit in
                Parliament? How could they do things with men? For there is this
                extraordinarily deep instinct, something inside one; you can't get over
                it; it's no use trying; and men like Hugh respect it without our saying
                it, which is what one loves, thought Clarissa, in dear old Hugh.</p>

                <p>She had passed through the Admiralty Arch and saw at the end of the
                empty road with its thin trees Victoria's white mound, Victoria's
                billowing motherliness, amplitude and homeliness, always ridiculous, yet
                how sublime, thought Mrs Dalloway, remembering Kensington Gardens and
                the old lady in horn spectacles and being told by Nanny to stop dead
                still and bow to the Queen. The flag flew above the Palace. The King and
                Queen were back then. Dick had met her at lunch the other day--a
                thoroughly nice woman. It matters so much to the poor, thought Clarissa,
                and to the soldiers. A man in bronze stood heroically on a pedestal with
                a gun on her left hand side--the South African war.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
