<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/​ns/​1.0'>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Homemade apple pie</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>BBC googfood</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <list>
                    <head>Ingredients</head>
                    <p>For the filling:</p>
                    <item><num>1</num> kg apples</items>
                    <item><num>140<num> g golden caster sugar</item>
                    <item>half teaspoon cinnamon</item>
                    <item><num>3</num> tablespoon flour</item>
                    <p>For the pastry</p>
                    <item><num>225</num> g butter</item>
                    <item><num>50</num>g golden caster sugar</item><note> You might need extra sugar</note>
                    <item><num>2</num> eggs</item>
                    <item><num>350</num> g plain flour</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Step 1</head>
                <p>Put a layer of <rs>paper towels</rs> on a <term>large baking sheet</term>. 
                Quarter, core, peel and slice the apples about <num>5</num>mm thick and lay evenly on the baking sheet. Put <rs>paper towels</rs>
                on top and set aside while you make and chill the <term>pastry</term>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Step 2</head>
                <p>For the <term>pastry</term>, beat the butter and sugar in a <rs>large bowl</rs> until just mixed.
                 Break in a <term>whole egg</term> and a <term>yolk </term>(keep the white for glazing later). 
                 Beat together for just under <num>1</num> min – it will look a bit like scrambled egg. Now work in the flour with a <rs>wooden spoon</rs>, 
                 a third at a time, until it’s beginning to clump up, then finish gathering it together with your hands. 
                 Gently work the dough into a ball, wrap in <term>cling film</term>, and chill for <num>45</num> mins. 
                 Now mix the <num>140<num>g/<num>5<num>oz sugar, the cinnamon and flour for the filling in a <rs>bowl<rs> that is large enough to take the apples later.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Step 3</head>
                <p>After the <term>pastry</term> has chilled, heat the <rs>oven</rs> to <num>190</num>C/fan <num>170</num>C/gas <num>5</num>. 
                Lightly beat the egg white with a <rs>fork</rs>. Cut off a third of the <term>pastry</term> and keep it wrapped while you roll out the rest, 
                and use this to line a pie tin – <num>20</num>-<num>22</num>cm round and <num>4</num>cm deep – leaving a slight <term>overhang</term>. 
                Roll the remaining third to a circle about <num>28</num>cm in diameter. Pat the apples dry with <rs>kitchen paper<rs>, 
                and tip them into the bowl with the cinnamon-sugar mix. 
                Give a quick mix with your hands and immediately pile high into the pastry-lined tin.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Step 4</head>
                <p>Brush a little water around the <term>pastry rim</term> and lay the <term>pastry lid</term> over the apples pressing the edges together to seal. 
                Trim the edge with a <rs>sharp knife</rs> and make <num>5</num> little slashes on top of the lid for the steam to escape. (Can be frozen at this stage). 
                Brush it all with the egg white and sprinkle with caster sugar. 
                Bake for <num>40</num>-<num>45</num> mins, until golden, then remove and let it sit for <num>5</num>-<num>10</num> mins. 
                Sprinkle with more sugar and serve while still warm from the oven with softly whipped cream.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>This recipe was written by <name>Angela Nilsen</name>. 
                For more information: <ptr target="https://www.bbcgoodfood.com/author/angelanilsen"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

        